<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Posts on Scott Jeen</title>
        <link>https://enjeeneer.io/posts/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Posts on Scott Jeen</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2021 16:33:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://enjeeneer.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
        <item>
            <title>The Role of Probabilistic Machine Learning in Climate Change Mitigation</title>
            <link>https://enjeeneer.io/posts/2021/01/the-role-of-probabilistic-machine-learning-in-climate-change-mitigation/</link>
            <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2021 16:33:12 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://enjeeneer.io/posts/2021/01/the-role-of-probabilistic-machine-learning-in-climate-change-mitigation/</guid>
            <description>🌍 If we are to successfully mitigate climate change we must reduce global emissions to near-zero by 2050. To this end, three solutions exist:
 Generate energy using emission-free technologies; Capture and bury emissions using carbon capture and storage (CCS); and Use energy more efficiently.  In the UK, emission reduction efforts via solution 1) have so far proven extremely successful. Emission-free energy technologies generated 45% of UK electricity demand in 2020 which has caused a decrease in grid carbon intensity of 66%.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="heading">🌍</h1>
<p>If we are to successfully mitigate climate change we must reduce global emissions to near-zero by 2050. To this end, three solutions exist:</p>
<ol>
<li>Generate energy using emission-free technologies;</li>
<li>Capture and bury emissions using carbon capture and storage (CCS); and</li>
<li>Use energy more efficiently.</li>
</ol>
<p>In the UK, emission reduction efforts via solution 1) have so far proven extremely successful. Emission-free energy technologies generated <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/statistics/energy-trends-section-6-renewables">45% of UK electricity demand in 2020</a> which has caused a decrease in grid carbon intensity of <a href="https://www.iea.org/countries/united-kingdom">66%</a>. Headway is being made, albeit slowly, toward solution 2), DRAX hope to deploy two Bioenergy CCS plants by 2030 that will remove <a href="https://www.theccc.org.uk/publication/sixth-carbon-budget/">0.32 tCO2 per person per year</a>. To date, mitigation efforts via solution 3) have proven less fruitful. UK final energy consumption has not meaningfully decreased in recent years; only 7% on 1990 levels according to the IEA. Despite widespread acknowledgment of the need to use energy more efficiently, over 30 years we&rsquo;ve made little progress.</p>
<p>Our inefficient use of energy is linked closely with uncertainty. We overuse our resources today because tomorrow&rsquo;s needs are difficult to predict. Building contractors, for example, pre-purchase more material than is required because they are unsure exactly how much they will use in construction. Similarly, supermarkets buy more food than customers want because they struggle to predict customer demand. And home owners use their central heating for longer than needed because they cannot be sure how long it takes to warm up. Better predictions of our uncertain future allow us to make informed, efficient choices in the present that mitigate wasted resource.</p>
<p>To make such predictions we use <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/nature14541">probabilistic machine learning</a>. And with our predictions, we can then think about ways of acting optimally in these futures using <a href="https://web.stanford.edu/class/psych209/Readings/SuttonBartoIPRLBook2ndEd.pdf">Reinforcement Learning</a>. For example, using a probabilistic forecast of this afternoon&rsquo;s cloud cover, we could predict when the solar panels on our roof are likely to produce energy and delay the use of air conditioners until then. Using predictions for control in such a way, we can reduce emissions at near-zero cost,  in a way that other mitigation strategies struggle to do.</p>
<p>My work is about making the best use of our predictive abilities to use resources more efficiently to mitigate climate change.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Book Review: Cradle-to-Cradle Remaking the Way We Make Things</title>
            <link>https://enjeeneer.io/posts/2018/11/book-review-cradle-to-cradle-remaking-the-way-we-make-things/</link>
            <pubDate>Tue, 20 Nov 2018 16:54:55 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://enjeeneer.io/posts/2018/11/book-review-cradle-to-cradle-remaking-the-way-we-make-things/</guid>
            <description>Consider the cherry tree. A frenetic supply chain of blossom that produces thousands of seeds in the hope that one might fall to the soil, take root and grow. Its manufacturing model is inefficient, wasteful and laborious, yet beautifully nourishing to its surrounding ecology. The blossom that do not germinate instead provide nutrients for insects, microorganisms, animals and soil; its abundance and over-production should not be chastised, but celebrated.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure>
    <img src="/img/cradle.jpg" width="250" height="350"/> 
</figure>

<p>Consider the cherry tree. A frenetic supply chain of blossom that produces thousands of seeds in the hope that one might fall to the soil, take root and grow. Its manufacturing model is inefficient, wasteful and laborious, yet beautifully nourishing to its surrounding ecology. The blossom that do not germinate instead provide nutrients for insects, microorganisms, animals and soil; its abundance and over-production should not be chastised, but celebrated. In Michael Braungart and William McDonough’s seminal book “Cradle-to-Cradle: Remaking the Way We Make Things”, the author’s ask: “What would the human-built world look like if it were built by a cherry tree?”. Braungart and McDonaugh assert that since the industrial revolution, humankind’s marriage with nature has been shaky and is now, in the 21st century, going through a messy, complicated divorce.</p>
<p>The authors argue that our conventional cradle-to-grave manufacturing and consumption processes are deeply flawed in their linearity and their contempt they show for the environment. They compel the reader to drive a personal and corporate paradigm shift toward a circular design economy – their so-called cradle-to-cradle (C2C) approach. Their manifesto for revolution asks that producers make three actions: one is to see waste as food for the environment; two is to separate biological and technical nutrients in products to ease ready recycling and upcycling; and three is to adopt eco-effective practices rather than eco-efficient practices that value and incorporate the environment in design. Central to the novel’s argument is the author’s criticism of western society’s obsession with death, indeed graves. They suggest that mankind is fixated on finding a grave for their products after their finite and often short useful life. Braungart and McDonough summarise their circular philosophy and set up their narrative by asking the reader “what if the industrial revolution had taken place in a society that believed in reincarnation? Would our cradle-to-grave approach become cradle-to-cradle?”</p>
<p>The concept of circularity was first discussed 52 years ago when Kenneth Boudling began questioning the linear openness of our economic activity in his piece “The Economics of the Coming Spaceship Earth” [1]. He identified society’s predisposition toward sending material to ‘sinks’ rather than reusing them in a closed economy. In 1989, this idea was further developed by Pearce and Kerry Turner when they first coined the phrase ‘circular economy’ [2],   after which Jackson synthesised much of the work in the field in his book “Material Concerns: Pollution, profit and quality of life” [3]. Thought toward bettering our products by copying natural design in the form of biomimicry was first discussed in 1982 by Merrill [4], before being popularised by Benyus in her seminal book “Biomimicry: Innovation Inspired by Nature” [5]. Cradle-to-Cradle’s call for ecological practice in industry and a closer alignment with nature draws heavily on these influences and preaches the author’s sermon in accessible English that resonates with academics, corporations and the public. In response to Cradle-to-Cradle, the Ellen Macarthur Foundation have furthered the shift toward a circular economy by producing a realisable framework that is founded on Braungart and McDonough’s cradle-to-cradle principles. The book has been cited thousands of times and has sold more than 300,000 copies worldwide. As such, it must be credited with starting a revolution in industrial design and in public discourse around societal overconsumption and waste.</p>
<p>Cradle-to-Cradle comments on various aspects of sustainability, notably: challenging orthodoxy through change, operating within environmental limits and enacting effective life cycle management. The novel-spanning motif that we must create a mindset shift toward waste equalling food is the clearest objection of orthodoxy. The authors are constantly challenging the idea of waste describing it as an artefact of human creation; “whatever humans make does not go ‘away’” they exclaim. They make the reader question where “away” really is; is a landfill “away”? Is a recycling plant “away”? Where is this abstract place? They emphasise that nothing enters or leaves the confines of our planet, thus we live in materially closed system. Braungart and McDonough state that “to eliminate the concept of waste means to design things – products, packaging and systems – from the very beginning on the understanding that waste does not exist”. Inoculating public and corporate minds with this message could be extremely powerful in catalysing the transition toward a sustainable circular economy and I believe this is the most influential, effective message from the book. The author’s exemplars of how we can make our waste nourishing and not damaging are often idealistic, particularly their assertion that we should design a car with clean water as effluent that could promote roadside ecology. Despite their head-in-the-clouds aspirations, I still feel this message is truly valuable. I would add that any efforts to shift the paradigm away from convention will inevitably seem utopic at first, but it is only by thinking laterally with great optimism that can we enact real change.</p>
<p>Throughout the text, Braungart and McDonaugh ask industry to design processes and products that operate within the environmental limits of the planet. They repeatedly remind the reader that “being less-bad is not good” referring to the environmental impact of our actions. They demonise so-called eco-efficiency, that is, for example: using less material in manufacturing, creating more carbon-efficient processes or using less water in agriculture. To that end, McDonough was quoted in an interview with the National Press Club as saying “If you want to go to Mexico, and you’re driving toward Canada, even if you slow down you’re still going to Canada”. Instead the authors ask the reader: “What would it mean to be 100% good?”, by that they mean operating with eco-effectiveness; designing systems so they are in deep symbiosis with nature. In doing so they say we can strive for a future of abundance, rather than one of limited eco-efficiency, bounded by the traditional environmentalist ideals of conservationism. The authors claim that their eco-effective principles will design systems that “pay back […] the environment with interest” and in my opinion this is where, their argument collapses.</p>
<p>Despite the authors giving thought to environmentalism at a systems level, I am not convinced the boundaries of their analysis are wide enough, and this particular utopic view is a clear example. It is thermodynamically impossible for a process to pay back the environment “with interest”, this would require it to add more energy to the environment than was taken in the first place. Sure, creating coffee cups that require few inputs to produce and can fertilise farmland when disposed would be excellent, and I welcome the innovation that cracks this perpetual motion-style problem, but these are impossibilities.</p>
<p>The author’s character assassination on eco-efficiency seems equally misguided. They state that we should build eco-effective buildings with green roofs that provide bird habitat and solar cooling, rather than designing more efficient air-conditioning systems or effective solar shades. Whilst I agree that green roofs bring positive benefits, the authors do not comment on the increased structural steel required to buttress these green roofs. What about the mineral extraction associated with this added steel? The carbon emissions produced in their manufacturing? The disposal of this steel at the building’s end of life? The bounds of their systems analysis appear blinkered. “Efficiency isn’t much fun” McDonough and Braungart assert. I would argue efficiency can be fun, as well as challenging and beneficial despite not paying back the environment with circular idealism. Strangely, the authors backtrack on their criticism of efficiency, concluding their comments by saying “This is not to condemn all efficiency. When implemented as a tool within a larger, effective system […] efficiency can actually be valuable”. Their lack of continuity in this argument is a damning indictment of their eco-effective propaganda.</p>
<p>Life cycle management is a third sustainability theme tackled by McDonough and Braungart’s Cradle-to-Cradle. They describe two component metabolisms from which products are formed: the biological cycle and the technical cycle, and they say that extending the useful life of a product is achieved by optimising products within these cycles. The biological metabolism consists of biological nutrients; materials that can be “consumed by microorganisms in the soil and by other animals”. Conversely, the technical metabolism is filled with technical nutrients that are man-made materials; industrial components. The authors suggest that we must keep these cycles entirely separate if we are to salvage and reuse components in new products. If we do not, we create products they describe as “monstrous hybrids”. McDonough and Braungart describe the modern leather shoe as a monstrous hybrid. Leather is, of course, a biological nutrient that would traditionally be coloured with a vegetable chemical: tannis. Recently, leather shoes have been coloured with chromium tanning, a technical nutrient, to avoid the energy-intensive process of extracting tannis from trees. Because these nutrients become intrinsically locked together, neither component can be salvaged at their end of use and their value is lost. I believe this analysis is extremely valuable in an engineering context as it requires that life cycle thinking is at the forefront of the designer’s mind at the earliest stage of a project, rather than an afterthought.</p>
<p>The authors use this analogy to comment on recycling, or a lack thereof, in industry more generally. They introduce the concept of “downcycling”, whereby valuable components are not reused in their original context, but downgraded to a rudimentary form; plastic water bottles are often melted down and moulded into speed bumps, for example. The authors tell the reader that separating the biological and technical metabolisms will in fact enable upcycling, whereby components can be used in applications better than their original use. What a wonderful idea! Components can be used again and again in ever-improving contexts. I struggle with this concept and find, once again, the boundaries of their system are conveniently limited. Thermodynamics is their recurring enemy, with the second law stating that everything tends toward disorder. Upcycling components to higher quality contexts, contexts of higher order, requires the input of energy – a distinct omission from their analysis. The recycling system becomes tricky when you consider the second law as all matter is freefalling into a cavernous well of disorder. In my opinion, we should strive for recycling in the same context rather than upcycling, but even this requires an energy input to maintain the same order or quality. I think it is unrealistic and uneconomic to expect that technical nutrients can be transformed to applications of higher quality – a practice that any corporate executive would endorse if he thought it were plausible – and believe it comes at the detriment to the authors otherwise effective observations on life cycle management.</p>
<p>Braungart and McDonough’s Cradle-to-Cradle is a seminal piece in the sustainability field that undoubtedly inspired the circularity movement and highlighted the wasteful consumption paradigm that plagues society. Their call for the reader to take inspiration from nature’s waste-free, abundant supply chains is effective as is their observations of the technical and biological metabolisms that contribute to our products. The author’s often utopic philosophies seem tricky to implement and their analyses appear limited, but their optimism about the future is refreshing in a world filled with negative rhetoric. A true strength of their message is the coherent language through which it is delivered, but I would argue that, despite the book’s accessibility, there are very few readers who can realistically enact the change they want. This power is inherently reserved for political leaders and captains of industry and their message offers few hand-holds for the general public to grip to. Nevertheless, Cradle-to-Cradle is an overwhelmingly positive contribution to sustainable thought that opens a dialogue with all stakeholders of the design process. If the cherry tree represents the ideal to which we aspire, Michael Braungart and William McDonough have planted the first seeds.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>[1]        K. E. Boulding, “The Economics of the Coming Spaceship Earth,” Environ. Qual. Grow. Econ., pp. 3–14, Mar. 1966.</p>
<p>[2]        D. W. Pearce and R. Kerry Turner, Economics of Natural Resources and the Environment. 1989.</p>
<p>[3]        T. Jackson, Material Concerns: Pollution, profit and quality of life. Routledge, 1996.</p>
<p>[4]        C. L. Merrill, “Biomimicry of the Dioxygen Active Site In The Copper Proteins Hemocyanin and Cytochrome Oxidase,” Thesis, 1982.</p>
<p>[5]        J. Benyus, Biomimicry: Innovation Inspired by Nature. William Morrow &amp; Company, Inc., 1997.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Plastic Politics</title>
            <link>https://enjeeneer.io/posts/2018/10/plastic-politics/</link>
            <pubDate>Fri, 19 Oct 2018 16:56:04 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://enjeeneer.io/posts/2018/10/plastic-politics/</guid>
            <description>Single-use plastics and the European Single Market have more in common than you may think; they were both popularised in the middle of the 20th century, they both bring economic benefit to western economies and they both have a party trying to discontinue their use. Negotiating the terms of my exit from the plastics market (read: Plaxit) has required diplomacy and strong leadership in equal measure. Admittedly, I have not penned a Chequers plan, nor have I travelled to Brussels for negotiations, but I have had to make compromises.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure>
    <img src="/img/plastic_politics.png" width="350" height="300"/> 
</figure>

<p>Single-use plastics and the European Single Market have more in common than you may think; they were both popularised in the middle of the 20th century, they both bring economic benefit to western economies and they both have a party trying to discontinue their use. Negotiating the terms of my exit from the plastics market (read: Plaxit) has required diplomacy and strong leadership in equal measure. Admittedly, I have not penned a Chequers plan, nor have I travelled to Brussels for negotiations, but I have had to make compromises. Sadly, the hard-Plaxit you readers have cried for is proving tricky to reconcile. Your brain may be filling with statements like: “Why are you even following through with this if you can’t do it properly?” or “You’ve fed us misinformation!” or “Why don’t you scrap the idea entirely?!” and all of these have validity. But we can’t go back now, that would be undemocratic. Or could we?</p>
<p>No we can’t. So I intend on playing the hand I’ve been dealt as best I can. The primary policy I am here to discuss relates to my use of University cafeterias. I am allowing myself to eat lunch, and occasionally dinner, in food halls provided the food I am eating is not observably housed in plastic at the point of eating. How’s that for policy design? Clearly, the issue is that the food on my plate, say the Lamb Tagine I had for dinner last night, will have been removed from plastic containment by chefs before it got to me. The Lamb may have come in some butcher’s paper (unlikely), but the cous-cous will have undoubtedly been poured from a plastic bag. I appreciate this is cheeky, but your author would like to eat something that isn’t loose vegetables for every meal – the modus operandi thus far. I should emphasise that other than this slight rule-bending, I am yet to buy any food or other goods delivered in plastic. I shall explain my progress to date.</p>
<p>I am practicing the obvious stuff that I’m sure many of you do too: carry a keep-cup for coffee, carry a steel water bottle, carry a cloth bag for any shopping and carry steel cutlery on the off-chance the only available cutlery is plastic. I have dealt with more subtle hurdles too, including: not eating crisps or chocolate, not eating meat, not eating pre-packed salads and not eating pre-made sandwiches or pastas for lunch. I have been primarily buying my food from the local farmer’s market (see below) as opposed to my nearest supermarket as said supermarkets are impossible to navigate without purchasing plastic – more on this in a future blog. Not only is the produce nicer than that of a supermarket, but there is of course benefit in supporting local farmers and businesses.</p>
<p>So, things are on-track (bar cafeteria-gate) and I plan on ramping up my change effort to affect those other than myself in the weeks to come. I hope you accept the requests outlined above, otherwise we will descend into an inevitable no-deal scenario and nobody wants that. Thanks for reading, I hope you stay tuned.</p>
<p>PS</p>
<p>As I was about to post this blog, there is <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-45911794">plastic-related news hot off the presses</a>. The Environment Agency have made accusations against UK recycling firms who are reportedly profiting illegally from recycling they aren’t even doing. As if you needed another reason to give up plastic entirely!</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Change</title>
            <link>https://enjeeneer.io/posts/2018/10/change/</link>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Oct 2018 16:55:47 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://enjeeneer.io/posts/2018/10/change/</guid>
            <description>What’s that Mahatmu Gandhi quote again? The one about changing the world and so-on? It never really resonated with me. It’s rather pessimistic, but I often succumb to Down’s paradox or the paradox of voting, that is, the disbelief that one’s vote can alter the outcome of an election or, crucially, that one’s actions can cause a tangible disruption to our environment. During my first 10 days at the University of Cambridge I have quickly (and quite rightly) felt my pessimism is unshared.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What’s that Mahatmu Gandhi quote again? The one about changing the world and so-on? It never really resonated with me. It’s rather pessimistic, but I often succumb to Down’s paradox or the paradox of voting, that is, the disbelief that one’s vote can alter the outcome of an election or, crucially, that one’s actions can cause a tangible disruption to our environment. During my first 10 days at the University of Cambridge I have quickly (and quite rightly) felt my pessimism is unshared. Academics and students here work tirelessly to make the world a better place and there is no doubt that countless individuals will indeed disprove Down’s paradox and enact change that benefits us all. These same academics have set my cohort a challenge to change one thing in our lives for the duration of this term to understand the barriers to change, both personal and external. This is a timely test given the IPCC’s recent report detailing our accelerated impact on the climate and the risks our actions pose to sea level rises, coral reefs, fisheries and agricultural land. The need for change could not be more acute.</p>
<p>It’s funny, my initial reaction upon hearing of our Change Challenge was one of opposition. Upon reflection, I am not particularly akin to change, nor am I any good at it. Joining the university is arguably the biggest change I have made in the last 5 years and, hilariously, prior to that, my biggest change was attending the university where I studied my undergraduate degree. I am capable of making small changes quite readily: do a bit of running, read more, travel to some new places, but I sub-consciously resist wholesale change. In fairness, I think most of us resist huge change too – the status quo is warm, comfortable and known. Indeed, I feel change resistance is a significant part of our evolutionary makeup. Older generations regularly lament how the world has changed and how younger people don’t act how they would like. This is understandable as their actions, and the way society operated in their youth, allowed them to survive (dare I say thrive!) and in many cases allowed them great wealth and opportunity. But the way we do things now needs not only to change, but be turned on its head. We cannot keep treating our planet the way we do if we want other generations to enjoy what we enjoy. This is hard! I quite like the warm, comfortable status-quo that is our CO2-asphyxiated home. But if we are going to change it we need people like me who don’t like change to really change the way we operate.</p>
<p>So I’ve decided for my Change Challenge I am going to attempt to give up single-use plastic entirely. I have chosen this not just for the obvious ecological benefits, but to change the way I currently interact with plastic. I want to view my world through plastic-tinted glasses, if you will.  I know the issues associated with this, namely that all of western society revolves around the use of plastic, but that is primarily why I am doing it. I want to do something that is really going to affect my lifestyle to challenge my resistance to change. I am also aware that this is essentially impossible given our extensive use of plastic in food packaging and hygiene products, but I imagine my attempts will more clearly highlight where we excessively use plastic and identify the low-hanging fruit for plastic reduction in such sectors. I intend to update this blog bi-weekly to discuss the difficulties I am having and perhaps offer some strategies for reducing our plastic consumption without going to such extremes as these.</p>
<p>Be the change you want to see in the world he said. This time, Gandhi, I’ll try and listen.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
